A Guide to the Military & Wartime Cookery Collection, 1884-1965 (Bulk, 1917-1945)
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Military & Wartime Cookery Collection, 1884-1965 (bulk, 1917-1945)
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2017-029
0.7 Cubic Feet 1 box
The Military & Wartime Cookery Collection consists of a variety of manuscript and ephemeral materials relating to the history of military and wartime food and cooking. Items in the collection date from 1884 to 1965, though the bulk of the collection covers parts of World War I through World War II (1917-1945).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Military & Wartime Cookery Collection was purchased by Special Collections in April 2017. Possible accruals may be added in the future.
Scope and Content
The Military & Wartime Cookery Collection consists of a variety of manuscript and ephemeral materials relating to the history of military and wartime food and cooking. Items in the collection date from 1884 to 1965, though the bulk of the collection covers parts of World War I through World War II (1917-1945). Formats and items include (but are not limited to) menus, U.S. Government publications from various agencies, corporate sponsored pamphlets, ration books, recipes, and a photograph album. While the majority of the collection relates to U. S. military and wartime cooking or food history in America, there are some items relating to British military or U. S. military abroad.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in series by conflict/era using the broadest wartime dates: The American Civil War (1861-1865); Mid- and Late 19th/Early 20th Century (1866-1914); World War I (1914-1919); Between the World Wars (1920-1938); World War II (1939-1945); Post-World War II (1946-). Within each time period, materials are grouped by format. Each folder has a list of individual items in the contents list of the finding aid.
Please note: materials are located within the conflict or era to which they are relate and may not date only from that specific time period. For example, the Civil War series contains menus from reunions that took place between 1884 and 1905.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
Other World War Food-Related Collections in Special Collections
Culinary Pamphlet Collection, c.1870s-1990s (Ms2011-002). Finding aid available online.
Food Advertisement Collection, 1894-1962 (Ms2017-020). Finding aid available online.
State/Regional Home and Agricultural Publications, 1934-present (Ms2012-040). Finding aid available online.
National Agricultural Publications, 1917-present (Ms2011-022). Finding aid available online.
World War II Sugar Rationing Pamphlets, 1941-1945 (Ms2015-048). Finding aid available online.
Separated Materials
The following books and publications were purchased as part of this collection and are cataloged for Special Collections Rare Book Collection. The list below is organized by conflict/era to reflect the organization of the manuscript materials. Within each era, items are listed in chronological order by publication date.
Pre-World War I Military (1897-1908)
General Orders No. 37, 1897
The Vital Question and Our Navy, 1898
The Army Baker: A Manual Prepared for the Use of Students of the Training School for Bakers and Cooks, 1908
World War I (1914-1918)
Recueil de Recettes Culinaires, c.1914-1918?
British French Italian Russian Belgian Cookery, 1916
Manual for Army Cooks, 1916
Mess Accounts and Messing, 1916
Manual for Army Bakers, 1917
War-Time Cook and Health Book, Lydia E. Pinkham Company, 1917
Food and Victory, 1918
How to Use Corn Meal, Oat Meal, Barley, Buckwheat,…,Royal Baking Powder Co., 1918
Mary Elizabeth's War Time Recipes, 1918
Official Recipe Book: What to Eat How to Cook It, 1918
Twentieth Century Club War Time Cook Book, 1918
Post World War I Military (1927-1939)
The Cook Book of the United States Navy, 1927
Favorite Navy Recipes, 1931
Army Chow, 1939
World War II (1940-1946)
Feeding the People in War-Time, 1940
Food in War Time, 1940
Manuel du Cuisinier a la Campagne, 1940
The Nation's Larder and the Housewife's Part Therein, 1940
Army Baker, TM 10-410, 1941
British War Relief Cookery Book, 1941
Favorite Navy Recipes, 1941
Old and New British Recipes Collected for Your Pleasure…, 1941
Two Hundred War-Time Recipes, 1941
American Woman's Cook Book, 1942?
The Army Cook, TM 10-405, 1942
Canned Food Manual, 1942
Recipes Complied by Fort Ord Army Daughters, 1942
Respectfully Yours, Annie, 1942
The Soldier and His Food, 1942
Albers Victory Recipes, 1943
The Bakeshop Trouble Shooter, 1943
Baking Manual for the Army Cook, 1943
Cooking Dehydrated Foods, TM 10-406, 1943
Cooking on a Ration: Food is Still Fun, 1943
Eat to Live: The Blue Book of Cooking, 1943
Food Planning for Victory, 1943
Vegetable Gardening in Wartime, 1943
Victory Vitamin Cook Book for Wartime Meals, 1943
Wartime Cooking Guide, 1943
War-Time Edition Russian Cook Book for American Homes, 1943
Fare-Ye-Well with Ladies of the Realm, 1944?
Food in War and in Peace, 1944
Health for All Wartime Recipe Book, 1944
Health for Victory Meal Planning Guide, March—June, August 1944
Victory Gardening, Cornell Extension Bulletin, 1944
You Said a Mouthful, 1944
The Cook Book of the United States Navy, 1945
The Impact of the War on Civilian Consumption, 1945
Manual of Army Catering Services Part II-Recipes, 1945
An Experimental Study of Rationing, 1946
Recipes Out of Bilibid, 1946
Food Facts for the Kitchen Front
120 Wartime Meat Recipes
164 Recipes/Recettes
Pillsbury's 40 War Time Recipes
Ration Time Recipes
Sun-Maid Wartime Recipes that Taste Good!
War Cook Book for American Women
Post World War II Military (1948-1990)
Naval Catering Handbook and Manual, BR 97 (48), 1948
Operation Vittles, 1949
A Cook's Tour of Quantico, 1952
Army Brats' Cookbook, 1953
Army Recipes (Meat, Poultry, Fish, Gravies, Sauces, and Dressings), TM10-412-1, 1957
Army Recipes (Eggs, Cheese, and Sandwiches), TM 10-412-2, 1957
Cooks' Tour, 1960
Army Recipes (Salads and Salad Dressings), TM10-412-4, 1961
NCOWC Souvenir Cook Book, 1962
Dare to Excel in Cooking, 1966
Peace de Resistance, c.1970
Military Lifestyle: Entertaining and Party Guide, 1990
Manual for the Chef of Staff
Index Terms
Subjects:
Civil War; History of Food and Drink; World War I; World War II
Genre and Form Terms:
Culinary pamphlets; Ephemera; Menus; Pamphlets
Contents List
- Wartime: American Civil War (1861-1865)
  - Civil War Reunion Menus, 1884-1905 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Society for the Army of the Potomac Fifteenth Annual Reunion, 1884-06-12
    - Receiption Banquet to General R. A. Alger, Commander in Chief, G. A. R., 1890-02-18
    - Forty-Second Anniversary 11th Mass. Light Battery, 1905-01-02
- Military: Mid-and Late 19th/Early 20th Century (1866-1914)
  - Menus, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Complimentary Dinner by the 999th Artillery Association to the Champions of the 2d Division Mass. Amateur Bowling League and the Champions of Inter-Club League, 1895-04-02
- Wartime: World War I (1914-1919)
  - Ephemera, 1918, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Training School for Bakers and Cooks Certificate of Proficiency (for Pvt. Robert B. Thomas), 1918-10-17
    - Welcome Home World War Veterans program (Milford, MA), 1919-06-09
    - Snoopy WWI RAF Towel, n.d.
  - Menus, 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Dinner, Thanksgiving Day, United States Naval Air base, Eastleigh England, 1918-11-28
    - 11th Engineers, Hotel Pennsylvania (New York, NY), 1919
  - United States Government Publications, 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "A Whole Dinner in One Dish," U. S. Department of Agriculture & U.S. Food Administration, 1917
    - "Forty Lessons in Gardening for the Northeastern United States," U. S. School Garden Army, Department of the Interior, 1919
- Military: Between the World Wars (1920-1938)
  - Menus, 1924, 1935
    - Thanksgiving Day, 28th Bomb Squadron, Camp Nichols (framed), 1924-11-27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Christmas Dinner, United States Ship Nevada, December 25, 1935
- Wartime: World War II (1939-1945)
  - Corporate Pamphlets, 1942-1944, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Ball Brothers Company, "Can with Less Sugar or Can Without Sugar," 1942
    - Charles B. Knox Gelatine Co., "Don't Let Butter Rationing Scare You!," 1942
    - Standard Brands Incorporated, "Ten Victory Cake Recipes," 1942
    - Pillsbury Flour Mills Company, Pillsbury's Fightin' Food Communique, No. 1, September 1943
    - Pillsbury Flour Mills Company, Pillsbury's Fightin' Food Communique, No. 3, November-December 1943
    - Pillsbury Flour Mills Company, Pillsbury's Fightin' Food Communique, No. 4, January 1944
    - Beech-Nut Packing Company, "Your Victory Garden Work Sheets," n.d.
    - National Live Stock and Meat Board, "Wartime Meat Extenders and Low-Point Meat Cuts," n.d.
    - Rockwood & Co., "Bits Sugar Savings Recipes," n.d.
  - Ephemera, n.d. (c.1941-1945) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Victory" geometric puzzle, n.d.
    - Wonderbread, "The Guide to United States Warships" (volvelle), n.d.
  - Menus, 1942-1945, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Cooley's (Evanston, IL), 1942
    - Emergency Menus (American Red Cross), January 1943
    - U. S. Naval Receiving Barracks, No. 3 (Auckland, New Zealand), Independence Day Dinner, 1943
    - French Lick Springs Hotel (French Lick, IN), 1944
    - Hotel New York (New York, NY), 1944
    - The Brown Derby (Hollywood, CA), 1945
    - Palmer House (Chicago, IL), 1945
    - The Corner, n.d.
    - Thanksgiving Day (Fort Lewis, WA), n.d.
  - Ration Books, n.d. (c.1941-1945) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Ramsey Family (Maine)
    - Perry Family (New Hampshire)
  - Recipes (Handwritten), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Handwritten recipe for "War Cake no eggs," n.d.
    - Handwritten recipe for "War Cake," n.d.
  - United States Government Publications, 1942-1946, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Recipes to Match Your Sugar Ration," Bureau of Home Economics, U.S. Deaprtment of Agriculture, & Office of Price Administration, 1942
    - "Vitamins from Farm to You," U. S. Department of Agriculture, 1942
    - "Wartime Canning of Fruits, Vegetables," U. S. Department of Agriculture, June 1943
    - "National Wartime Nutrition Guide," U. S. Department of Agriculture, July 1943
    - "National Food Guide," U. S. Department of Agriculture, August 1946
    - "Fats in Wartime," Massachusetts State College, U. S. Department of Agriculture, & County Extension Services, n.d.
    - "Keep the Home Fires Burning," Massachusetts State College, U. S. Department of Agriculture, & County Extension Services, n.d.
- Military: Post-World War II (1946-)
  - Menus, 1947, 1953, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Sachers British Army Officers Hotel (France), 1947-01-12
    - U. S. Hotel Thayer (West Point, NY), 1953-10-15
    - The General von Stuben (Wiesbaden, Germany), n.d.
    - Officers Club (Fort Amador, Panama Canal Zone), n.d. (likely after World War II)
  - Yokota Air Base Commissary Photograph Album (3 folders), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 14-16)
    The album primarily contains a series of photographs of the Yokota Air Base Commissary, taken c.1965. Images include staff, "action" shots of shoppers, displays, and spaces. In addition, there is a series of 8x10 black and white portraits of military officers. The second half of the binder contains mimeographed pages on the Japanese language and culture.